Guide to the R. B. Holmes photographs, 1910-1919 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
R. B. Holmes photographs 1910-1919 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Holmes, Randolph Bezant, 1888-1973.
3.5 linear feet Extent: 92 Items
Commercial photographer active in Pakistan, India, and Afghanistan during first half of the 20th century. Collection of ninety-two 11.5 x 9.5" black-and-white photographic prints of Afghanistan, India, and Pakistan. The images were taken by British photographer R. B. (Randolph Bezzant) Holmes and possibly others from his studio who traveled with him. Holmes was the owner of the R. B. Holmes & Co. photography studio in Peshawar, Pakistan. The majority of these detailed images were taken during the end of the Anglo-Afghan war in 1919 and depict large British military camps and vast landscapes, sometimes with camel caravans or military convoys. Some scenes show the remains of villages, military features such as towers, and religious structures. There are also portraits of individuals along with scenic views. Several of the images have been hand-tinted, probably by Holmes himself. Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts.
RL.00590
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The R. B. Holmes Afghan War Photographs were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 2009, 2010, and 2011.
Biographical Note
Randolph Bezzant Holmes was born in 1888. He was a commercial photographer who took over the business established by his father, William D. Homes, around 1899 in Peshawar, Pakistan. Holmes was an official photographer of the Afghan Wars on the North West Frontier in Afghanistan. He also spent time in Kashmir and in other Asian locales. Later in life he also painted watercolor landscapes from the same areas. In 1929 he published a memoir of his time in Afghanistan, Story of the North West Frontier Province, Peshawar, containing gelatin print plates of his landscapes. Holmes died in 1973.
Collection Overview
Collection of ninety-two 11.5 x 9.5" black-and-white photographic prints of Afghanistan, India, and Pakistan. The images were taken by British photographer R. B. (Randolph Bezzant) Holmes and possibly others from his studio who traveled with him. Holmes was the owner of the R. B. Holmes & Co. photography studio in Peshawar, Pakistan. The majority of these detailed images were taken during the end of the Anglo-Afghan war in 1919 and depict large British military camps and vast landscapes, sometimes with camel caravans or military convoys. Some scenes show the remains of villages, military features such as towers, and religious structures. There are portraits of individuals, including camel drivers, a sniper, a female spinner, a young woman dressed in traditional wear, and various groups. The landscape views include the Khyber Pass, Tanai Gorge, Kabul River, Khargali Ridge, Dal Lake, Nanga Parbat, and the Sikkim Himalaya. Military camp views, many in panoramic scale with fine detail, include Landi Khana, Dakka Plain, and Landi Kotal.
The majority of the prints contain an identification number originally marked on the negative, and the prints are arranged in numerical order accordingly. A list of the prints created from the studio's original list of commercially available prints, with captions and numbers when available, is in each of the boxes in the collection. There are a few images that do not appear on this list but have numbers assigned to them, and some are entirely unnumbered. Items not on the original list have been placed in the collection according to their subject matter. There are duplicate copies of several images. Also, some of the images have been hand-tinted, probably by Holmes himself. Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts.
Subject Headings
Holmes, Randolph Bezant, 1888-1973; Great Britain. Army -- History -- 20th century; R. B. Holmes & Co. (Peshawar); Afghan Wars; Afghan Wars -- Pictorial works; Afghanistan -- Pictorial works; Pakistan -- Pictorial works; India -- Pictorial works; Afghanistan -- Social conditions -- 20th century; Pakistan -- Social conditions -- 20th century; India -- Social conditions -- 20th century; Black-and-white photographs.
Related Material
R. B. Holmes Collection (papers and photographs)
Macmillan Brown Library, University of Canterbury, New Zealand
Contents of Collection
- R. B. Holmes photographs, 1910-1919 and undated, (3 boxes)
  Print numbers were assigned by the photographer; an original list of complete prints, with numbers, offered by the studio for commercial purposes is included in the box. There is also an annotated copy of this list that reflects the library's holdings.
  - Jamrud Fort and entrance to the Khyber Pass. (2 copies, one housed with Print 9), 1 (Box 1)
  - Entering the Khyber Pass. Camel Convoy., 2
  - Ali Musjid Camp., 3
  - Exit of the Khyber into the Peshawar Plains. (2 copies, one housed with Print 35), 4
  - Looking North through the Gorge at Ali Musjid., 5
  - Looking South through the Gorge at Ali Musjid. (Two copies, one housed with Print 15), 6
  - Camp at Landi Kotal (left half of panorama)., 7
  - Camp at Landi Kotal (right half of panorama)., 7a
  - Looking towards the water works on the road to Landi Khanna., 9
  - On the road to Landi Khana looking towards Kbargali ridge., 11
  - Looking through the Tytler Gorge towards Landi Khanna., 15
  - Looking through the Tanai Gorge towards Landi Khanna., 16
  - Khargali Ridge and Bagh (left half of panorama)., 18
  - From Kafirkote over looking the Khargali Ridge. The battle-ground of the 11th May 1919, Bagh Springs and village in the distance and remains of old Budhist Stupa on extreme left., 20
  - From Kafirkote towards Dakka. Kabul river in the distance and remains of old Grecian Fort wall on near hill., 21
  - Entering the Dakka Plain., 22
  - Untitled. Dakka camp, Kabul River?, 25
  - Untitled. Dakka camp, Kabul River?, 25a
  - Dakka camp, Kabul River., 26
  - Dakka camp showing Fort Robart and Kabul river., 27
  - Looking across the Kabul river, showing ferry., 31
  - After bombardment view of Loe Dakka and the main road showing deserted villages towards Landi Khana., 32
  - A view of villages in the Khyber., 35
  - Looking towards Jallalabad. Taken from a picquet during an engagement., 37
  - Tribal towers and villages., 51
  - A general view of Ali Musjid from the fort., 58
  - Landi Khana and tribal villages. (2 copies), 70
  - Khyber Pass near Landi Khana., 73
  - The end of the caravan crosses into Afghanistan from the Khyber., P.5
  - In the Hingis Tangi. (2 copies), 84
  - Looking across the Tank Zam towards Jandola., 85
  - Entering the Ahnai Tangi., 88
  - Looking through the Ahnai Tangi (near)., 89
  - View from Piaza Raghza towards Pir Gul. (2 copies), 92
  - Jirga with Kaniguram in back ground., 98
  - Waziri caravan types., 114
  - The Waziri. (hand tinted), 117 (Box 2)
  - The Old Pathan., 122
  - A Pathan Woman., 124
  - Two Afghans., 126
  - Two Afghans with their camels., 127
  - The Sniper., 131
  - Afridi Man., 131a
  - Pathan woman spinning., 132
  - On the Dal Lake, Srinigar. (hand tinted), 161
  - Looking from Zojila to Baltal, 1,500 feet below., 170
  - Camping ground at Panjitarni, one march before Amarnath., 174
  - By Tannin River and Mountain heights in mist., 180
  - Pastoral scene at Aro, Liddar Valley. (hand tinted), 209
  - View near Rampore. (hand tinted), 1062
  - Pahlgam., 1084
  - Gamp Forest, Phalgam., 1084a
  - The Liddars. (hand tinted), 1089
  - Club and Nedou's Hotel, Gulmarg., 1106
  - Ploughing, the Kashmir homestead. (hand tinted), unnumbered
  - Sind Valley, Kashmir. (hand tinted), unnumbered
  - Dal Lake. (hand tinted), unnumbered
  - Nanga Parbat 26, 660. The east aspect across the Astor River., unnumbered
  - Glacier Valley and campsite, Sonemarg, Kashmir. (hand tinted), unnumbered
  - Parachinar Bazar., 260 (Box 3)
  - Deserted tribal fort near Guja Chinar in the Spin Tangi., 268
  - Kurram Militia Post., 269
  - A defile in the Kohat Pass. (hand tinted), 279
  - Looking down on Kala Bagh and Mari Indus., 300
  - Looking towards Khirgi from Manzai., 301
  - Village tower by Jandola. (2 copies), 303
  - Jandola Fort. (2 copies), 304
  - Jandola Camp., 305
  - In the Shahur Tangi., 306
  - Exit of the Shahur Tangi (distant)., 307
  - Exit of the Shahur Tangi (near)., 308
  - Character Study; Wana Waziris., 333
  - Kaur Bridge Fort., 385
  - Manzai., 386
  - Sararogha Camp., 392
  - Typical Mahsud and Waziri tribesmen., 431
  - Character study "The Mahsud." (hand tinted), 432
  - Bathing Ghats on the Ganges river-Benares (hand tinted), 902
  - The Khan of Dir welcomes the Viceroy with great pomp-the Panjkora river borders the valley with Hindu Kusk in the distance. (hand tinted), 1420
  - Return of Mohforce, Oct. 1935. New Road, Nahakki Pass. (hand tinted), unnumbered
  - In the Sikkim Himalaya, view towards Darjeeling. The pony track winds over the ridges., unnumbered
  - The Indus. Baltistan. The pony track runs along the river bank. (hand tinted), unnumbered
  - Untitled. Mountain and river scene., unnumbered
  - Open Road, Afghanistan, 1910., unnumbered